My name is Michel Blomgren and my
passion is wilderness survival...
...the art of keeping yourself alive
under harsh circumstances.
This is the first episode in a series about
survival and the outdoors in Sweden.
This episode takes you through five points
that increases one's chances in the Wild.
To better illustrate these points, I'll take
you through a typical survival situation...
...lost in the woods in Autumn.
SURVIVAL
with Michel Blomgren
As you probably understand, this guy
is lost.
He was just out for a short hike but took
the wrong path somewhere along the trail.
As he consider himself to know the area
quite well, he tries to walk out...
...but what he as of yet hasn't realized is
that he's been walking around in circles.
He's not prepared and lacks map, compass
cellphone, whistle or gear for sleeping out.
Is he going to wander about the woods
until nightfall?
Is someone from civilization going to
report him missing?
Are they going to look for him in the
right area?
The answers to these questions can make
a difference between life and death.
He still hasn't given up on the idea that
he might get out before dark...
that's why he's trying to walk out. The
darker it gets the more stress he feels.
Panic is an emotional reaction, an alarm,
that mobilizes the organism to fight or flight.
To feel panic is nothing wrong, it's
completely normal.
The reason for panic is fear, fear is like fire:
It can warm you, but also burn you down.
Just like fire should be respected,
so should also fear.
No one is fearless, everyone are fearful.
There are only 2 kinds of people: Those who
can control fear and those who can not.
Thinking you are either one or the other
is wrong!
We are both kinds depending on the situation
and how that situation affects our emotions.
(humility for the task)
The first rule when lost is not to get more lost.
When panic creeps up on you, imagine a
STOP sign.
Point 1: STOP stands for
Stop, Think, Orient, Plan
Stop, don't increase your physical activity
that will only generate more stress.
Sit down, breath deeply
do not hyperventilate!
If panic takes control over you rather than
you over it, you're GAME OVER...
...even if you're the greatest survival
expert in the world!
If you've got a thermos with something hot,
drink it, but slowly.
If you're exhausted and breathing heavily,
do not eat, it's just going to make it worse...
...just like walking and eating at the same
time is exhausting.
Think through your situation and orient
yourself.
What time is it? How many hours of daylight
do I have? What gear do I have? Where am I?
How did I end up here? Can I get home
before nightfall?
If I don't get out, what do I do then?
Is someone going to report me missing?
In that case, when?
Is my last known position anywhere near
where I reported I would be?
Make a time plan where it says: If I don't
get home by X o'clock, I'm going to...
make an inventory, find or build a shelter,
light a fire and collect a lot of firewood...
The most difficult decision you can make
is decide to spend the night in nature.
It's much easier to push on thinking
"I'll eventually get out."
Perhaps it's most important to realize
that you have to make that decision...
...then the mind can prepare for
both alternatives, stay or go.
If you wander around for several hours
without finding something you recognize...
...then it's time to prepare for the inevitable,
spending the night in nature.
The earlier you realize you won't get out,
the more time you have to prepare.
Point 2: Do not give up! Survival is 80%
in your head, only 20% physical.
Back to our lost friend, he has stopped and
is starting to think.
Fractions of thoughts are rushing through
his head - it is time to focus!
Let's take a look at his gear...
The most important gear is the one we're
wearing, clothes.
Man's natural climate is 27 degrees C,
right now it's -3 degrees Celsius.
This means we must maintain a difference
of 30 degrees in order to stay warm.
Hypothermia is the main killer in the
Wilderness on European latitudes...
...both because of cold,
but also because of rain/water.
Water can conduct heat away from the
body up to 27 times faster than air.
For this reason it is extremely important to
be able to build a shelter and make fire.
In the next episode I'm going to
demonstrate gear in greater detail.
If protection against rain and cold is
priority one, then water is priority two.
Dehydration is very common in outdoor
activities.
Water is something we can not be without
for more than a few days.
It is very unlikely that you will die of
starvation in a typical survival situation.
Humans can survive over 40 days
without food!
The gear that our lost friend has with
him is minimal...
...but if it's used correctly it will save his
life during the coldest point of the night.
A poncho of the American type is not
only rain gear, it's also a shelter.
It's big enough and has grommets in each
corner.
The poncho is actually the only shelter I
bring, even in normal outdoor activities.
Works great, gear with more than one use.
Extra dry clothing is very important.
Longjohns are underestimated. In cities
you can see people with polar jackets...
...but on their legs they have tight jeans
or thin pants for tropical climate.
Longjohns of wool or fleece under a pair of
wind-proof pants keep the blood warm...
...all the way to the feet.
Water is priority 2 after we can keep warm. A
thermos with something hot is nice in the cold.
We need to consume about 3 liters of water
during a normal not very physical day,
according to most recommendations.
I conducted a 5 day exercise during the
summer of 2005 with very little food.
I soon noticed that I was drinking too much,
so I cut down to 1 liter per day.
That was enough for that specific situation.
I recommend to drink more, especially
in Winter, when dehydration...
...make hypothermia worse.
If you feel headache, drink lots of water.
Headache is one of the first signs of dehydration
and then you're already 2-3 percent dehydrated.
The color of urine should be clear, not
dark yellow - then you're dehydrated.
When drinking enough you can think clearly,
very important when lost in the woods.
Never ration water, we don't have a water
reserve like we do a fat reserve.
To neglect dehydration almost makes you
get used to it.
It will end with passive behavior
and eventually collapse.
Many streams below the mountain region
in Sweden are contaminated with...
parasites, bacteria, etc.
It's important (as hygiene in general is) to
clean water before drinking it.
All pathogens have an incubation period
before symptoms of disease appear.
The time can vary from hours to months.
The most common pathogens, the protozoans
and the bacteria...
have an incubation time around 2 days or
more (Salmonella strikes within hours though).
In Sweden this, statistically, means you will
get rescued before disease appear.
Despite this, water ought to be treated as
the disease that may strike back in the World
...may be very painful.
Bad diarrhea, bleeding intestine,
vomiting, are some symptoms.
Boiling is, despite many modern solutions,
the best way to make water safe to drink.
In order to boil water you need something
to boil in, a metal mug isn't all that wrong...
...but a cooking pot, like a coffee pot,
is much better.
Food isn't bad, but we can survive many
days without something to eat.
The hunger can be challenging after
8 hours since our last meal...
It can rumble a lot in the stomach.
Some time later it will decline and the
hunger becomes much more bearable.
The will to eat can be strong even during
the initial period, but can later transform...
into nausea. 1 of 20 vomit after 2-3 days
without food.
When the energy, the carbohydrates, are low
we can no longer work as fast as before.
It's very important not to work harder
than the body can handle in order to...
...prevent becoming dizzy or even faint.
Ration the body's energy reserve by
walking and working slowly.
Survive longer - be cool. Work
determined but slowly.
When you've established yourself in
nature there's no reason to run around.
Point 3: 3 of something is a distress call.
3 blows in a whistle, 3 light signals, SOS, etc.
In order to protect ourselves against the
weather we need to know about hypothermia.
Convection: typically responsible for 50%
of our heat loss.
Convection means air around us and in
between layers of clothing blows away...
by cold air and movement. Warm air is lighter
than cool air and moves away from the body.
Radiation: typically responsible for 30%
of our heat loss.
Heat (energy) is transfered to the colder
environment, even through clothing.
Heat radiation can be felt from the Sun
and from fire.
Respiration: typically responsible for 10%
of our heat loss.
The cold air we breath is heated in the
airways before reaching the lungs.
Evaporation: typically responsible for 5%
of our heat loss.
Heat is transfered away from the body
through the process of vaporization of liquid.
Sweat and wet clothing is the main reason
for evaporation.
Conduction: typically responsible for 5%
of our heat loss.
Heat energy is transfered from a warmer
material by direct contact with a colder one.
Heat is always transfered from a warm
place to a colder place.
To know what not to get in contact with
is important.
Water can conduct heat away from your
body up to 27 times faster than air.
Aluminium can conduct heat about
100 times faster than ice.
No good idea to use an aluminium blanket
as sleeping mat, especially not in winter.
Point 4: 4 chores...
Shelter, Fire, Water, Signal for help
To choose a good spot for camp is
essential.
It should be close to water but
preferably not right next to a lake.
Cold air sinks down over lakes at night.
Enough firewood nearby is essential. In
Sweden a spruce forest is a good place.
Spruce can be used in shelter building,
making of a "sleeping mat" and fire.
If you lack string, you'll find it under
ground. Spruce roots are excellent...
as long as the ground isn't frozen.
During winter it's important to carry string
with you - especially up north.
Necessity is the mother of all invention,
it doesn't take long to find a string to use.
In short... you use what you got.
The poncho protects against wind & rain.
It's time to protect against the cold ground.
Spruce bows can be used to make an
excellent traditional bush bed.
Make sure the curve of the bow points
upward to help raise you from the ground.
This will create an air layer between you
and the ground, just like a sleeping mat.
The amount of bows is very important,
it's good if the bed reach your knees.
The "spruce bow mattress" will sink a lot
when sleeping.
Please observe: The Swedish "Right to
Public Access" does not include taking...
spruce roots or spruce bows. Ask
permission from the land owner.
When lost for real you should break all
laws necessary to survive - it's your right.
You should be free as long as you can
defend your actions.
An English expression says more than
1000 words...
Better be tried by twelve,
than carried by six.
A good proverb in survival situations is:
Proper preparation prevents poor performance
especially when it comes to fire.
I'm collecting stones to make a fireplace.
A stone fireplace protects against ground
fire. The fire heats up the ground...
and ignite roots that smolder for days
that can turn into a nasty forest fire.
A stone fireplace also make the fire burn
more efficiently than on the (wet) ground.
This is the result. Most importantly,
stones in the bottom.
The fireplace is placed no more than an
arms length from the shelter in order to...
be able to feed the fire from the shelter,
but not too close to catch spit from the fire.
It's time to collect fire wood...
Not all wood will do. We'll need different sizes.
Twigs light branches that light bigger wood.
First focus is the tinder which will light
the first twigs.
Birch bark is an incredible material that will
burn even after being submerged in water.
By scraping the surface into a fine material
you can easily light it with a fire steel.
The dry twigs under most spruces is
excellent kindling when dry.
Dry spruce twigs are excellent first fuel
to the fire.
Birch twigs that have dried in the sun burn
well even after rain.
The bark protects the twigs from getting
wet.
Birch is excellent fire wood and can be
used even if birch contains a lot of water.
Many people say you can't use birch
unless it's -10 degrees C, but it does work.
If you can't find spruce twigs or birch
bark, you can make feather sticks.
Split wood burns much better than wood
that has not been split.
The wood is usually wet on the outside,
but dry on the inside.
This can be done with any kind of wood
and can even be lit with a fire steel.
You need to make several feather sticks
and split wood small to get a good result.
Once the fire is burning it's time to boil
a hot drink.
When water boils heavily it's safe to drink.
Big bubbles, no troubles is a good rule.
A tea of pine, or in this case, spruce
needles is an excellent forest tea.
To me, this drink symbolizes the sub-
arctic forest.
Instead of collecting single needles, take
whole twigs, preferably the tips.
The needles are rich in vitamin C during
Autumn, Winter and Spring.
Two hands full of needles to 1/2 liter
water will cover 1/3, or 20 mg...
of the Swedish recommended daily
intake of vitamin C.
10mg is however enough to keep scurvy
away, if you're going to be lost for months.
The needles also contain a small amount
of sugar which has a refreshing effect...
especially when tired and hungry. It
should boil for 20 minutes before served.
If you have a thermos, like our lost friend,
it's a good idea to fill it with this tea...
excellent to drink when freezing in the
middle of the night.
All is well that ends well. It doesn't
always end well though.
Who lives and who doesn't sometimes
make no sense what so ever.
Experienced outdoorsmen have perished
after just one night lost in the wild,
despite decent weather, clothing, good
gear and being physically unharmed.
While children under 6 years of age, even
infants, have survived extreme ordeals.
The will to live can not be taught, trained,
or learned by reading a book.
Each one of us must find our reason(s)
to live.
Perhaps it's enough to realize that one
want to live to survive?
The only thing one really need is the
ability to adapt to the new conditions...
that a survival situation has to offer.
5, the last point, the gear I consider
valuable in every outdoor activity.
Gear will only help the one who wants
to survive. Give up and gear is useless.
1) A good knife is your best friend
2) 2 means to make fire, a primary
and a secondary
3) A whistle is heard much further than
the voice, and lasts much longer too
4) A compass to navigate straight through
the forest
5) A first aid kit
I'm going to finish up by repeating my
5 points.
But first I want to thank you for watching!
1) STOP - Stop Think Orient Plan
2) Do not give up!
Few have died fighting on, many by giving up!
-- Swedish Defense Survival Handbook
3) Three of something is an international
distress signal
4) Four chores in a survival situation
Shelter
Fire
Water
Signal for help
5) Five things one should always carry
in the woods...
Knife
Two ways to make fire
Whistle
Compass
First aid kit
More episodes in this series can be
found on www.bushcraft.se
Filming, editing and music
by Michel Blomgren