Damn, I have to hold [the camera]
with one hand - this doesn't work well...
The big surprise...
All gear down with us.
- So, how does it feel?
You have not eaten in how many hours?
- 24 hours without food, except
some yoghurt this morning.
- Yes, except some yoghurt.
- I'm a little blurry...
- The brain isn't very fast... I'm tired.
- Very tired.
- The food fantasies are already evident.
- It's wet, everything is completely wet.
...it's depressing.
- How the hell can it smoke that much?!
- Damn smoke signal fire wood.
- Well, what's for dinner today?
- I can always eat the Polypody I found.
- It's Polypody and the last energy bar.
...unless we can find something more.
- Myself have this to eat...
Emergency food rations.
...it's what I've got to eat...
...and some gruel.
Enough for... two, three cups or something.
So it's something like...
1000 kcal or similar.
What have you brought to eat?
- I brought 2 of these. I ate one
earlier today.
It's an energy bar.
It contains about 200 kcal.
Only one left, but I also have one
of these...
It's a kind of gel... fast energy.
Before the abseil tomorrow I'm going to
abseil this down my throat...
So my head is a bit more clear.
So far we've only found Polypody,
hope we can find something more to eat...
...if not, I'm going to be hungry.
- Boil pine needle tea later.
- Pine needles, yummy yummy yummy
- Mmmm...
Manufactured February 1987.
Vintage food!
- Is it wet?
- Naa, barely raining.
It's nice, lucky we're dressed right for
this kind of weather.
- Exactly.
- I wouldn't want to be dressed in cotton
right now.
- Yes, that would've been cold.
- It's us they're hunting, huh?
- How have the night been anyway?
- The night have been good the first
6-7 hours.
The rest of the time my feet were
freezing.
Made a fire and tried to sleep next to it
as much as possible.
Made a fire... sleep...
wake up... freezing my feet again...
Just repeat. That's how fun it is...
I have a bad headache because I haven't
been drinking enough.
We're going to rappel soon...
within an hour.
- Within an hour? We'll see how that go...
- I'm going to eat my last energy gel.
- !?!@!
- It doesn't taste good?
- It says "strawberry flavour"
- Na, the taste was no hit.
- What? That bad?
The taste isn't sweet or what?
- Na... maybe... it tastes like...
- Let me taste some...
- It's like a concentrated juice mix
without water.
- No, it wasn't very nice.
- That's what you get for eating the last
energy bar yesterday.
- Rock n roll!
- We just got to find the right spot.
- Ready for this?
- Absolutely!
- Aha, you're filming?
- Yes.
- I'm trying to film too, but I really
need two hands to work the rope.
- Haha, well hello!
- Call of nature. I thought I'd wait till you
got down, but it took too long.
- Yeah, I'm too slow.
- Cool!
- Damn rubber band.
- So... now the... survival weekend is over...
almost anyway.
- Almost, not until I get something to eat.
- No, of course.
- Kebab pizza was it?
- Mmm... think so!
- As greasy as I can get it.
- Exactly.
- How long is it since your last real
meal?
- I haven't eaten real food for...
soon...
24 hours... hell no... it's 48 hours...
since I had a real meal.
Last time I ate... what was it...
Yesterday... at 09:00 was the
last time I ate something.
After that I have only eaten roots...
and my damn energy bars...
...which I am very tired off right now.
To eat real food again...
I feel quite good... I only have
headache because of dehydration.
...otherwise I feel OK.
- Mm
- The film shouldn't become a
feature (long) film.
- I was fishing here this summer.
- OK.
- How does it taste with real food?
- Very nice actually.
- Can't *!?@! speak properly...
- Damn it's good...